Guide to the Edwin Raymond Le Count Papers 1886-1935
University of Chicago Library
Le Count, Edwin Raymond. Papers
1886-1935
Crerar Ms 16
2.5 linear feet (3 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
Edwin Raymond Le Count (1868-1935) pathologist, academic, and resident at Rush Medical College. The collection includes correspondence, notebooks, writings, newspaper clippings, drawings, legal documents and ephemera. Materials date between 1886 and 1935. The majority of the materials date between 1910 and 1930. The papers provide insight into Le Count’s activities both at the university as well as within the field of scholarship, particularly as detailed through his correspondence with others in the field.
Information on Use
Access
The collection is open for research.
Biographical Note
Edwin Raymond Le Count was born April 1, 1868, in Fond du Lac, Wisconsin. Le Count studied medicine and pathology at Carroll College in 1886-1887. Following this he attended various universities, including Rush Medical College, John Hopkins University, the Pasteur Institute in Paris, and the University of Berlin. While he was raised in Wisconsin, Chicago became the city where he spent the majority of his career. In 1892, Le Count became a resident at Cook County Hospital as well as a professor of Pathology at Rush College.
Le Count’s medical career extended to positions as the Attending Pathologist in Cook County Hospital, the Presbyterian Hospital, St. Luke’
In 1910, Howard Taylor Ricketts, a friend and colleague of Le Count, died unexpectedly from typhus fever, which Ricketts studied. This tragic event greatly affected Le Count and his fellow academics. Le Count assisted in the organization of the Ricketts Fund meant to assist with memorial costs.
In 1934, Le Count received the James E. Stacey Award for his research. Within the same year, his health began to fail. Edwin Raymond Le Count died in 1935.
Scope Note
The Edwin Raymond Le Count Papers are organized into two series: Series 1: Personal; Series II: Professional; Series III: Oversized. The collection includes correspondence, notebooks, writings, newspaper clippings, drawings, dinner invitations, various certificates, contracts, legal documents, and his certificate of membership as a Free Mason. Materials date between 1886 and 1935. The majority of the materials date between 1910 and 1930. The papers provide insight into Le Count’s activities both at the university as well as within the field of scholarship, particularly as detailed through his correspondence with others in the field.
Series I, Personal, contains personal letters, drawings, newspapers he kept, dinner invitations, social gathering requests, programs from events attended, correspondence with Dean Lewis, materials related to the organization and collection of the Ricketts Fund.
Series II, Professional, includes documents and records relation to Le Count’s professional life. It contains correspondence concerning research and academia, acceptance into different conferences and journals, article request, legal and government documents, Le Count’s personal writings and two notebooks.
Series III, Oversized, contains the largest materials in the collection. They include certificate of admission to academic societies, certificate of commission as Pathologist Attending at Cook County Hospital, high school diploma, M.D. diploma, and a certificate of medical license.
Related Resources
Browse finding aids by topic.
Subject Headings
Le Count, Edwin Raymond, 1868-1935; Cancer
INVENTORY
- Series I: Personal
  - Short biography, invitations, fishing license 1886-1934 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Photographs and Newspaper Clippings 1902-1934 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Personal Correspondence 1898-1935 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Personal Correspondence with Dean Lewis 1916-1935 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ricketts Memorial Fund 1909-1911 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Series II: Professional
  - Professional records, correspondence 1886-1909 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Professional records, correspondence 1910-1914 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Professional records, correspondence 1915-1919 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Professional records, correspondence 1920-1929 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Professional records, correspondence 1930-1935 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Article Requests and Reprints 1904-1935 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Government and legal documents 1911-1929 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Le Count Writings 1910-1935 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Le Count Notebook Undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Le Count Notebook, class notes Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Series III: Oversized
  - Oversized materials 1883-1921 (Box 3, Folder 1)